GATACHA GODFREY

+254-724 305 719 | ggatacha@gmail.com

Professional Summary

I am a health systems Consultant with more than ten years of healthcare leadership. I have worked as a technical leader in health technologies assessment, program planning, monitoring and evaluation for health programs in middle and senior health management roles. I am a trained health economist with diverse experience in designing and undertaking economic evaluations, budgeting and financing for healthcare systems, monitoring and evaluation of programs, program management and research. I have a background training in accounting and auditing which is critical in supply chain system in finding, stopping fraud and eliminating systemic errors hence protect revenue and reputation. I have consulted for over 30 companies in my more than 10 years of service. I am self-motivated and excellent in working with others to achieve program objectives on time.

Expertise: Research | Health Finance | Health Technologies Assessment | Health Systems Strengthening | Entrepreneurship | Management | Strategy

Experience

HEALTH CONSULTANT | 05/2011 - Current

Kenya Agricultural/Health Initiative (KAHI)

- Provision of technical support to integrated and coherent planning, implementation monitoring and reporting across different thematic areas in health systems research
- Designing and undertaking economic evaluations including cost analyses, cost-effectiveness analysis, budget impact analyses, and local capacity building training of high-level health system stakeholders on HTA and evidence-based decision making
- Conceptualize, develop and promote strategies for different research areas
- Develop data collection tools
- Carry out quantitative and qualitative data collection
- Analyze qualitative and quantitative data
- Prepare and submit research papers for publication as required
- Formulation of concept notes, proposals, reports and policy briefs for various intervention areas
- Use of research findings, conclusions and recommendations to inform policy and decision making
- Take part in departmental annual work plan formulation as well as other project documents
- Provide support in strategic linkages and collaborations between KAHII and other partners including government, non-governmental organizations among others
- Stakeholder Engagement including conducting stakeholders' workshops, training and dissemination workshops
- Quality assurance checks of research and program documents
- Assist in development of monitoring indicators and evaluation plans for interventions
- Annual work plan monitoring, reviews and reporting
- Timely synthesis and submission of quality and accurate reports
- Linking work plans with corresponding Monitoring, Evaluation and Research (MER) plans
- Offering strategic guidance to partners including government in developing performance monitoring frameworks and baseline surveys
- Develop capacity development tools, including training materials and packages
- Promote the awareness of shared responsibility of M&E among all staff members through communication, training, learning and development activities through seminars, journal clubs and peer to peer learning sessions

SENIOR FIELD RESEARCHER | 05/2013 - Current

Sanisphere International - Paris, France

- Setting up a monitoring and evaluation plan for ad-hoc
- Developing specified project implementation plans and time frames
- Preparing job descriptions and budgets for projects in conjunction with directors of operations for different project regions
- Approaching regulatory and professional bodies to get clearance and approval for specified projects
- Conducting full cycle recruitment and training for specified project roles in collaboration with requiting agencies
- Coordinating specific project implementation including building in-process quality checks, quality improvement plans and training of team members where necessary
- Preparing project reports, financial reports and mid-cycle evaluation reports to both project team and company directors
- Conflict management within team and relationship management with commercial clients, implemenation partners and other stakeholders to ensure all are updated on the project progress
- Liaising with data processing teams to ensure timely delivery of relevant project data, reports and other requirements
- Winding up projects in time and on budget and ensuring the participants are well rewarded, the project
 objectives are met and end of project evaluation is done, reports prepared and submitted to directors and other
 partners
- Conducting qualitative research through interviews and focused group discussions.

CONSULTANT- SUPPLY CHAIN | 02/2015 - Current

Careplus Limited

- Ensure compliance with regulations
- Design ethics and appropriate procedures and policies
- Promote rationale and safe use of medicine
- Quality Assurance of products
- Supervise importation and storage of drugs
- Design standards of operations
- Carry out pharmacovigilance
- Advise of product recall protocols, market expansion strategies

MEDICAL SUPERINTENDENT | 01/2015 - Current

Murang'a County Government

- Oversee the day-to-day running of all clinical departments through supervision, mentorship and coordination of forty-six (46) health facilities in Murang'a County, Kandara Sub County
- Offer strategic leadership in planning for primary health services in the facilities
- Organize and participate in regular continuous medical education sessions with various clinical teams on a wide variety of health topics
- Participate in various regional and national technical working groups (TWG's) and provided mentorship to clinicians of all cadres through scheduled and non-scheduled support supervision
- Liaison with government institutions and other stakeholders to create collaborations in various hospital programs as well as community outreach programs
- Conception and submission of donor funding proposals
- Timely preparation and submission of quarterly and annual reports
- Data analysis to inform service delivery improvement as well as forming the basis of evidence-based programming and service delivery
- Budgeting and Planning
- Resource mobilization as well as quarterly budgeting and allocation of resources to different departments
- Ensure prudent use of hospital resources, providing oversight to financial management through ensuring adherence to laid down government financial procedures and budget monitoring
- Quality control support through development and implementation of standard operating procedures (SOP's)
 and tools necessary for training, service provision, quality assurance, monitoring and evaluation and commodity
 management.

TECHNICAL ADVISOR (HEALTH ECONOMIST) | 10/2018 - Current

Murang'a County Government

- County Health Planning, Budgeting and Financing Technical Lead; Murang'a County I was the technical advisor
 to the County Health Management (CHMT) team in planning, financing, monitoring and evaluation for health
 services by using approaches rooted in locally generated data
- This included: preparation of the County Annual Work Plan for Health, the County Health Strategic Plan and the
- County Health Monitoring and Evaluation & Framework
- Conducting monitoring and evaluation for primary healthcare services including utilization of key health metrics, guiding data collection and analysis, and sharing of findings periodically with relevant stakeholders
- Providing technical advisory support and develop facility plans to improve primary healthcare services i.e
- Need analysis as indicated from the M&E reports
- Leading reviews of financial reports based on contractual obligation
- Team lead in monitoring the spending of donor funds and other county expenditures and disbursement
- Developing and monitoring the county's Monitoring, Evaluation, and Providing guidance and communication to the CHMT and development partners on program evaluations
- Supporting the county to improve efficiency in planning, budgeting and financing for health services considering finances provided for by local partners, the National Health Insurance Fund (NHIF) and local revenue to make strategic purchasing of primary health care services
- Supporting the development of innovative mechanisms to increase demand for primary health services
- Reviewing public financial management procedures and by-laws relating to health financing in the county, with a view of suggesting a way to domesticate them to suit local circumstances and advocate and facilitate reforms as appropriate
- Providing technical support to the implementation of government and donor plans at the county level
- Supporting budgeting for primary health services in the annual work-planning cycle, and supporting the
 utilization of funds dedicated to primary healthcare services by: providing technical advisory support in the
 development of annual work plans; supporting the introduction of output-based payments (including but not
 limited to those based on NHIF income) into county planning; supporting the use of funds from the Global
- Global Financing Facility (GFF) to incentivize improved uptake of RMNCAH activities, finalizing donor and
 program reports (both narrative and financial); ensuring use of relevant evaluation findings, conclusions and
 recommendations are incorporated into program reporting; reviewing progress reports submitted by partners
 and providing feedback to improve quality and timeliness of reporting; identifying and disseminating good
 practices, lessons and knowledge as identified through program implementation, monitoring and evaluation
 activities, Taking part in identification of skills or knowledge gaps and addressing the same through staff capacity
 building and training

SENIOR PHARMACIST | 04/2012 - 12/2016

Ministry of Health (MOH)

- Leadership in Provision of Cost Effective, Quality pharmaceutical Services at Maragua District Hospital, Muriranjas District Hospital, Thika District Hospital, and St Mary's Cottage hospital.
- I was involved in streamlining and improvement of revenue collection at the department, leading to overall improvement of revenue systems in the hospital
- Provision of administrative oversight in running of the department including advising the medical superintendent on strategic direction, ensuring adherence by all departmental staff to the laid down hospital and county policies in service delivery, staff appraisal
- Leading in development of annual work plans as part of a team, ensuring the same are congruent with the annual targets, donor and county government expectations
- Part of the hospitals' Health Management Team
- Writing and implementing research proposals for the purposes of improving health service provision in the sub county
- Planning, implementation and evaluation of patient care.
- Quality Assurance of products and creating a comprehensive drug therapy plan for patient specific problem
- Identification of goals of therapy and reviewing all prescribed medication and monitoring potential drug interactions and adverse drug reactions

Core Qualifications

- Project management
- Change management
- Risk assessment
- Performance management
- Stakeholders management
- Strong decision maker

- Complex problem solver
- Innovative
- Service-focused
- Computer skills proficient in Word, Excel, Power-point, Internet
- Analytical packages (SPSS, R)
- Accounting packages (Quick-books, Sage and Pastel)

Education

Kenya School of Government

Strategic Leadership Development Program, 2020

University of Nairobi - Kenya | Master of Science

Health Economics and Policy, 2019

Chartered Management Institute

Management and Leadership, 2017

University of Nairobi - Kenya

Bachelor of Pharmacy, 2011

Strathmore University

Certified Public Accountancy- CPAK, 2008

Accomplishments

- Best field Researcher- Sanisphere International (2013-date)
- Servier International Scholarship Award for top students (University of Nairobi)
- Best presentation in International Pharmaceutical Students Federation Conference (2011-Thailand)
- Chair for Accounting and Auditing committee, ICPAK
- I am self-motivated and excellent in working with others to achieve program objectives on time.
- Computerization of commodities inventory control system in G.o.K primary health care facilities and Hospital pharmacy, drug stores, and other consumer departments at Muranga County
- Consultant in Civil Society Organisations; UNGASS Kenya/Brazil project on Reproductive Health Rights Advocacy
- Awarded best Head of Department by Muriranjas District Hospital Management Team during the financial year 2013/2014.
- Member Pharmaceutical Society of Kenya-organizing CMEs and CPDs.
- Initiation of community pharmacy in G.o.K Hospitals to improve equitable universal access of pharmaceutical commodities not supplied through EMMS- KEMSA supply chain.
- Training Pharmacist and pharmaceutical interns on rational drug use, inventory control systems, handling
 psychotropic and narcotic substances, EMMS supply chain management, Good Dispensing Practises, ART
 commodities management, Support supervision in Rural Health Facilities (Health Centres and Dispensaries),
 Clinical Pharmacology-Adverse Drug Reactions monitoring and reporting.
- Pharmacovigillance-reporting of ADRs and QA/QC of pharmaceutical commodities.
- T.o.T in Commodity management (ART, EMMS, TB, RH-FP, Vaccines), Malaria, HIV and Aids, TB, NCDs, infectious diseases, clinical management, quality improvement, EMONC, National referral systems, Drug and Substance Abuse Prevention and Kenya Quality Model for Health.

Personal Information

Nationality: Kenyan

References

- Dr. Fredrick Omondi (Director)
 Sanisphere International
 +254-720 616 649
 <u>frederick@omondi@sanisphere.com</u>
- Dr. Victor Kibe (Director)
 Kenya Agricutural Health Improvement Initiative
 +254-726 674 401
 victorkibe@gmail.com
- Dr. Tessy Oranga (Deputy County Pharmacist)
 Murang'a County Referral Hospital
 +254-721 263 699
 cesca.ces@gmail.com